<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Poems on Gil Locaylocay Caley</title>
        <link>https://www.kalanggam.com/categories/poems/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Poems on Gil Locaylocay Caley</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 23:05:30 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.kalanggam.com/categories/poems/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Hey Girl</title>
        <link>https://www.kalanggam.com/post/hey-girl/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 23:05:30 -0500</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.kalanggam.com/post/hey-girl/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;hey girl,&lt;br&gt;
you remind me&lt;br&gt;
that i have two hearts,&lt;br&gt;
two kasingkasings whose beats sing&lt;br&gt;
for you, for me, for us, for we,&lt;br&gt;
brown girls and brown queers, who rise&lt;br&gt;
like the sun after gentle rains and eastward winds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hey girl,&lt;br&gt;
you remind me&lt;br&gt;
of the south plains sky,&lt;br&gt;
stretched wide over the lands,&lt;br&gt;
colonized, where we rebelliously learned&lt;br&gt;
to thrive, to live, to flourish, to give&lt;br&gt;
to all society&amp;rsquo;s cast aside, all who have lived and died&lt;br&gt;
and will live again on the breath of justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hey girl,&lt;br&gt;
you remind me&lt;br&gt;
that we have high hopes,&lt;br&gt;
manifested destinies and techniques&lt;br&gt;
to achieve all the dreams, at first unimaginable&lt;br&gt;
by our ancestors, by our lovers, by our oppressors, by our detractors,&lt;br&gt;
culturally rich and getting richer, immeasurable&lt;br&gt;
like the grains of rice from the eons harvested over paddies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hey girl,&lt;br&gt;
you remind me&lt;br&gt;
that our words are more powerful&lt;br&gt;
than any fist, any sword, any bomb, any gun—&lt;br&gt;
that our hearts beat louder than any boots, drums, or speakers.&lt;br&gt;
you remind me that our spirits fight harder&lt;br&gt;
for love and for liberation, for life and for nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hey girl,&lt;br&gt;
you reminded me&lt;br&gt;
to stay connected even over sea,&lt;br&gt;
to practice my meditations and see the unseen.&lt;br&gt;
you reminded me to fight&lt;br&gt;
until we are all free.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Every Summertime</title>
        <link>https://www.kalanggam.com/post/every-summertime/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2023 23:05:25 -0500</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.kalanggam.com/post/every-summertime/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;every summertime&lt;br&gt;
i always think of your&lt;br&gt;
glistening forehead, of the queen city&lt;br&gt;
southern solstice summer sun on your freckled cheeks&lt;br&gt;
and your eyes hopefully honing in on my heart,&lt;br&gt;
where all your american dreams lay their heads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you are always dancing to the radio in my heart,&lt;br&gt;
in our cramped one-bedrooms,&lt;br&gt;
off potholed streets all over town.&lt;br&gt;
we are forever united at the asian king buffet&lt;br&gt;
by prawns and crab carcasses,&lt;br&gt;
under the grand opening banner which has been up&lt;br&gt;
all spring, the pepsi-blessed, post-racial future&lt;br&gt;
where you eternally wipe the mucus from my nose,&lt;br&gt;
clipping my hair til it can stand on its own two strands,&lt;br&gt;
and hold my head close and hand&lt;br&gt;
me a plate of palabok at parties to protect&lt;br&gt;
myself, messy in many multitudes of methods and means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i want only to wither with the burnt rice in the backyard,&lt;br&gt;
but every day you save and redeem me&lt;br&gt;
you say &amp;ldquo;you’re all i have,&amp;rdquo; i cry, cry, and cry&lt;br&gt;
i cry and still you esteem me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;because every summertime is movies and malls&lt;br&gt;
and mother and son&lt;br&gt;
getting picked up from school in your &amp;lsquo;06 kia spectra.&lt;br&gt;
nothing more magical than the way you love me.&lt;br&gt;
i’m terrified knowing that one day you will be done,&lt;br&gt;
but please still kiss my forehead, number one,&lt;br&gt;
and pretend i’m seven again,&lt;br&gt;
and let me live forever&lt;br&gt;
in your summertime.&lt;br&gt;
in every summertime you called me &amp;ldquo;langga.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Self-Effacing</title>
        <link>https://www.kalanggam.com/post/self-effacing/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2023 22:55:15 -0500</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.kalanggam.com/post/self-effacing/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was born beneath the rocks of a single-minded destiny: cutting cords.&lt;br&gt;
Sharpened by the first hominins to loosen them from their cages,&lt;br&gt;
with no mind to the wrath beset, on mnemonic devices or lexical anchors,&lt;br&gt;
or the amnesia befallen on transient states, belonging to history&amp;rsquo;s annals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was configured beneath the waves, with patterns of curls and divergences,&lt;br&gt;
for disfiguring fjords and highlands, for turbulently separating archipelagos.&lt;br&gt;
Lamentations are forgotten by the riverbed, rested as recanted, condolences&lt;br&gt;
to my estranged siblings. Generational recessions of pride trapped in our throats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be untangled from pain, to be freed from freedom,&lt;br&gt;
striking entries from an endless list of somewheres.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
